[
    {
        "question": "Gif monnes (<em>tunge</em>) #### biþ of heafde oðres monnes dadum don, gebete him mid .lx. scill — If a man's tongue is struck from the head by another man's deeds, compensate him with 60 shillings",
        "correctAnswer": "tunge",
        "explanation":"Here 'tunge' is the subject and so takes no new ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "God betæhte þæt mare leoht þæt is seo sunne to þæm dæge ond þæt læsse leoht þæt is se (<em>mona</em>) #### to ðære nihte — God assigned the greater light, that is the sun, to the day, and the lesser light, that is the moon, to the night",
        "correctAnswer": "mona",
        "explanation":"Here 'mona' is the subject and so takes no new ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se (<em>cempa</em>) #### oferwon frecnessa fela — The champion overcame many perils",
        "correctAnswer": "cempa",
        "explanation":"Here 'cempa' is the subject and so takes no new ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>Culfre</em>) #### is bilewite nyten ond fram geallan biternysse ælfremed — A dove is a meek animal and a stranger to the bitterness of gall",
        "correctAnswer": "culfre",
        "explanation":"Here 'culfre' is the subject and so takes no new ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ac Albanes slaga ne moste gesundful libban forðam þe him burston ut butu his (<em>eage</em>) #### ond to eorðan feollon mid albanes heafde — But Alban's slayer was not allowed to live in health, because both his eyes burst out of him and fell to the earth with Alban’s head",
        "correctAnswer": "eagan",
        "explanation":"Here 'eage' is both a subject and plural, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'eagan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Æt helle duru (<em>draca</em>) #### eardigaþ — Dragons dwell at hell's door",
        "correctAnswer": "dracan",
        "explanation":"Here 'draca' is both the subject and plural, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'dracan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>eage</em>) #### sind flæscene ond teð bænene — Eyes are of flesh and teeth of bone",
        "correctAnswer": "eagan",
        "explanation":"Here 'eage' is both the subject and plural, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'eagan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se Halga Gast wæs æteowod ofer Criste on his fulluhte on anre (<em>culfre</em>) #### anlicnysse — The Holy Ghost appears over Christ, at his baptism, in likeness of a dove",
        "correctAnswer": "culfran",
        "explanation":"Here 'culfre' is in the genitive and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'culfran'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Gefyrn scean leoht ingehydes geond þære (<em>eorðe</em>) #### ymbhwyrft —  Of old the light of knowledge shone over the circumference of earth",
        "correctAnswer": "eorðan",
        "explanation":"Here 'eorðe' is in the genitive and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'eorðan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Þonne bið seo sunne be seofonfealdum beorhtre þonne heo nu sy ond se mona hæfð þære (<em>sunne</em>) #### leoht — Then will the sun be sevenfold brighter than it now is, and the moon will have the light of the sun",
        "correctAnswer": "sunnan",
        "explanation":"Here 'sunne' is in the genitive and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'sunnan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He ne hierþ nanes (<em>wita</em>) #### word — He didn't hear any advisor's words",
        "correctAnswer": "witan",
        "explanation":"Here 'wita' is in the genitive and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'witan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðu fortrydst leona ond (<em>draca</em>) #### — You shall be a treader down of lions and dragons",
        "correctAnswer": "dracena",
        "explanation":"Here 'draca' is in the genitive and plural, so it takes the 'ena' ending to become 'dracena'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Gelyfde an ðara (<em>cempa</em>) ####, ðæs nama wæs Romanus, and cwæð to þæm Godes cyðere, 'Laurentie, ic geseo Godes engel standende ætforan ðe' — One of the soldiers, whose name was Romanus, believed, and said to the martyr of God, 'Lawrence, I see God's angel standing before thee'",
        "correctAnswer": "cempena",
        "explanation":"Here 'cempa' is in the genitive and plural, so it takes the 'ena' ending to become 'cempena'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Þara (<em>cnapa</em>) #### ðe binnan syxtyne geara ylde wæron hund-nigontig ðusenda hie tosendon to gehwylcum leodscipum to ðeowte — Of boys who were within sixteen years of age, they sent ninety thousand to all nations in slavery",
        "correctAnswer": "cnapena",
        "explanation":"Here 'cnapa' is in the genitive and plural, so it takes the 'ena' ending to become 'cnapena'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Saulus heold ðara leasra (<em>wita</em>) #### reaf ond heora mod to þære stæninge geornlice tihte — Saul held the garments of the false witnesses, and zealously instigated their minds to the stoning",
        "correctAnswer": "witena",
        "explanation":"Here 'wita' is in the genitive and plural, so it takes the 'ena' ending to become 'witena'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðas ðry dagas wæron buton (<em>sunne</em>) #### ond monan ond steorran ond eallum tidum gelicere wægan mid leohte ond þeostrum aðenede — Those three days were without sun and moon and stars, and all the hours, stretched out with light and darkness in equal balance",
        "correctAnswer": "sunnan",
        "explanation":"Here 'sunne' is in the dative and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'sunnan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða het se casere his (<em>hunta</em>) #### hine ðær gefeccean ond hine mid sweorde ofslean — Then the emperor bade his hunters fetch him there and kill him with a sword",
        "correctAnswer": "huntan",
        "explanation":"Here 'hunta' is in the accusative and plural, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'huntan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "God him sette (<em>nama</em>) #### Adam — God gave him the name Adam",
        "correctAnswer": "naman",
        "explanation":"Here 'nama' is in the accusative and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'naman'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða easternan tungelwitegan gesawon niwne (<em>steorra</em>) #### beorhtne — The eastern astronomers saw a new bright star",
        "correctAnswer": "steorran",
        "explanation":"Here 'steorra' is in the accusative and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'steorran'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "On þæm ylcan dæge he geworhte ealle (<em>steorra</em>) #### ond tida gesette — On the same day he created all stars and established hours",
        "correctAnswer": "steorran",
        "explanation":"Here 'steorra' is in the accusative and plural, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'steorran'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "God gesceop us twa eagan ond twa (<em>eare</em>) #### twa nosðyrlu twegen weleras twa handa ond twegen fet — God gave two eyes and two ears, two nostrils, two lips, two hands and two feet",
        "correctAnswer": "earan",
        "explanation":"Here 'eare' is in the accusative and plural, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'earan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðær wæron gecype (<em>oxa</em>) #### ond scep ond culfran ond þær sæton myneteras — There were oxen, sheep and doves for sale, and there sat moneyers",
        "correctAnswer": "oxan",
        "explanation":"Here 'oxa' is in the accusative and plural, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'oxan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ezechias eac asende his (<em>wita</em>) #### mid hæran gescrydde to þæm witegan Isaiam — Hezekiah also sent his counsellors clad in haircloth to the prophet Isaiah",
        "correctAnswer": "witan",
        "explanation":"Here 'wita' is in the accusative and plural, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'witan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He betæhte lamb to his (<em>cnapa</em>) #### ond se cnapa hit ofsloh — He gave a lamb to his boy and the boy slew it",
        "correctAnswer": "cnapan",
        "explanation":"Here 'cnapa' is in the dative and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'cnapan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Gif ic þisum (<em>draca</em>) #### to forswelgenne geseald eom, hwi sceal ic elcunge þrowian for eowerum oferstealle? — If I am given to this dragon to be swallowed, why should I suffer delay through your presence?",
        "correctAnswer": "dracan",
        "explanation":"Here 'draca' is in the dative and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'dracan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic ðe ofer (<em>eorþe</em>) #### geworhte, on ðære ðu scealt yrmþum lifgan — I created you on earth, on which you shall live in misery",
        "correctAnswer": "eorþan",
        "explanation":"Here 'eorþe' is in the dative and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'eorþan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ælfred cyning sende þa scipu to þæm (<em>muþe</em>) #### — King Alfred sent the ships to the river-mouth",
        "correctAnswer": "muþan",
        "explanation":"Here 'muþe' is in the dative and singular, so it takes the 'an' ending to become 'muþan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Abraham ferde mid twam (<em>cnapa</em>) #### to fyrlenum lande — Abraham went with two boys to a distant land",
        "correctAnswer": "cnapum",
        "explanation":"Here 'cnapa' is in the dative and singular, so it takes the 'um' ending to become 'cnapum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Anhyrne deor þæt deor hæfð ænne horn bufan ðæm twam (<em>eage</em>) #### swa strangne and swa scearpne — A one horned deer, that deer has one horn above the two eyes so strong and so sharp",
        "correctAnswer": "eagum",
        "explanation":"Here 'eage' is in the dative and singular, so it takes the 'um' ending to become 'eagum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    }
]